Hello, I'm Gunho Shin from DAY1COMPANY.
Today's topic is "Highly Advanced AX is Indistinguishable from Entrepreneurship."
I made the slides quite wordy, but since the presentation materials will be shared afterwards,
I wrote detailed content so you can understand by reading it.
Let me proceed quickly.
There are three things today.
First, I'll share what I learned while missing AX opportunities,
and ultimately explain that highly advanced AX is indistinguishable from entrepreneurship.
From that perspective, I prepared this presentation to share the AX playbook rules I came up with.
I'll talk more about the third point later,
but since this is Echo & Delta, I'm here to claim I'm an AX consultant.
So I brought my career path briefly.
The characteristic of a consultant is always having a broad and shallow skillset.
Currently, I'm the head of DAY1COMPANY's B2B business division,
and I'm working with the assignment to generate revenue or operating profit.
So I'm doing BD.
What's actually scary is what I felt while doing BD for a year.
I worked logically. So what?
I solved problems. So what?
Did you generate revenue and operating profit? Having to answer that is really scary.
If that doesn't come out, 100 people's salaries depend on me,
so 2025 was a year of tremendous pressure.
Before that, I was a PO at doeat and did consulting for over 2 years.
Then I did Python-based modeling in the financial sector and wrote some code,
and then at KAIST I engaged with machine learning and deep learning,
and have a background of installing that mindset as an engineer.
So now in the company, I'm a division head, so my role is to bring in money.
Interestingly though, it is an environment where I can immerse myself in the topic of AX.
So because we provide AX education comprehensively to enterprise-level customers,
I end up hearing a lot about what AX needs exist at the large enterprise level.
After all, providing AX education means they want to do AX.
I naturally heard those needs, but of course they're vague.
The education they want is also vague.
By meeting early adopter-type customers and diagnosing and structuring those needs,
I tell them "you need this kind of education,"
and it feels like we can just do a new business combining consulting and build services.
So I'm trying to launch it next year.
If internal customers are on the left, internally for me,
the goal isn't to achieve AX but to make money.
But ultimately, the best number one way to increase productivity in this era is AX,
so I did all sorts of things to increase productivity.
Internal education alone doesn't increase productivity just by doing it,
so I thought I should make it myself.
So I made and deployed projects,
like Gems, GPTs projects, dashboards, agents that create agents, Gems, GPTs, etc.
I tried hard to deploy them.
In November this year, I officially set up an AI Transformation team.
Naturally, as Donghoon mentioned,
resources aren't sufficient.
Whatever you do, bring in money.
Because of this, I can't starve myself and close my eyes,
so I just picked the 4 smartest people from the education team,
reassigned them, and although they didn't know n8n, they started studying.
Now after various trial and error,
we're completely rebuilding the proposal workflow.
From when leads are collected to the final proposal that goes to customers,
we're making it output as PPT.
And it's working better than expected.
So this is what I'm doing with AX right now.
My core question is: how can we succeed in AI transformation?
And beyond increasing individual productivity,
how do we get to the organizational level?
That's the question I have.
Probably everyone here today has the same question.
This is the technology adoption curve.
Where do you think you are among those attending today?
You're probably here, naturally.
What I felt when doing AX meetings or education meetings with large companies
and looking at internal business members
is that for those of you here, it's about here.
You're ridiculously extreme outliers,
but where is my team leader?
From a business perspective, if the team leader is here, thank you.
And the marketing team, education team, sales team that need to do AX,
if they're here, thank you.
To go beyond individual productivity to organizational productivity,
you have to force this on these people.
I have to do it.
I have to do all this to these people,
and usually that's the case.
Why am I getting tangled up with you?
Ultimately, it's a very difficult task.
And C-level people don't easily give resources.
From that perspective,
unless you're in a leadership position in this era, the opportunity itself
to try organizational-level productivity through AX
is only 2-3 tries even for leaders.
So what I want to say is,
because it's this difficult,
if I share what I learned from successful and failed AX,
we can reduce that trial and error,
waste fewer tickets,
that's what I think.
What I did first
was start with thinking
"I should make a proposal search system" beyond education.
I started from there.
So we have a workflow where our education consultants hear customer needs
and propose by introducing education.
At first, I proceeded by the book.
Naturally, I captured the workflow from interviews.
Then I drew it all out.
When this exists, I made about 4 agents
that draw it like this,
so when this goes in, it comes out like this.
I made it thinking "how impressive."
Naturally, after analyzing the workflow,
what do they tell you to do next?
They tell you to analyze bottlenecks.
So when I looked, ultimately
in collecting internal materials,
they were spending too much time.
Depending on the customer's key points,
the proposals to reference are all different,
but they're all on Drive, about 300 of them.
You have to open and look at them all,
so I thought "This is perfect low-hanging fruit for AX."
So I made it.
The resources I invested were:
At that time, there was a strategy team.
Practitioner interviews, the strategy team
summarized, I planned,
and the product group leader developed it.
First deployment, feedback, second deployment, but
then it failed.
No one really uses it now.
It's just abandoned.
Anyway, there was one
failed AX case.
But then
the second one among various attempts
that succeeded was
a service called skill consulting,
which has a pipeline.
Just doing AX on this service
was a successful experience.
To explain simply,
skill consulting is
for a battery solution company,
a company that does electric vehicle batteries,
in their R&D division,
80 teams, about 100 job functions,
defining the software skills
needed for R&D
and creating an education system.
It takes 18 weeks or something like that.
What I want to say is,
if a big department store like this
says they'll do skill consulting, you can leave it to the team,
but since I was a consultant,
I had a gut feeling that if I left it as is,
there would be trouble.
At minimum, 4 people would be invested for two weeks,
and even pulling all-nighters, time would be insufficient.
At this time, there was no
workflow analysis.
I just wrote all the logic
from start to finish, created agents,
and deployed it with vibe coding
all the way to creating interview sheets.
Naturally, in that process,
I also worked with GPT
to create questions
for establishing logic as a consultant.
And I developed this directly.
But
then
after creating this difficult consulting
work, the entire AS pipeline,
I ran about 5 iterations
by myself.
Creating logic and seeing the output all the way to the end,
thinking "Oh, the logic is
too heavy," coming back and going from start
to end to end. But what was really interesting was
that when consulting,
you can't run these iterations. Unlike development.
People have to do manual labor
for a long time,
and you can only see results after 8 weeks.
But now working with AI,
I ran it 5 times
and deployed it to the team.
So I spent 5 hours every Saturday
alone making this workflow,
and it's very accurate. 5 GPTs are
connected, and you put JSON from number 1
into number 2, and put JSON from number 2
that GPT analyzed
into the next result
consecutively, and when you upload it here,
it creates interview sheets in Excel.
In a way, it's
a much more unfamiliar
new workflow than the existing
proposal search system,
so I wondered
if the people actually doing this work
would use it,
but this was actually a huge success.
Everyone switched. They just use it
even though they don't know what JSON is.
Just on this webpage,
a link. When I worked in the business division,
if I went in with this link
and said "please use this," they would never use it.
They're just abandoned links,
but this one, everyone actually used it so much
that everyone switched to the new workflow.
So now
the decisive difference is just one thing.
First,
I learned that the magnitude of efficiency determines
AX success.
Looking at what failed,
the existing proposal selection time was about 1 to 2 hours,
and using this would reduce it to about 15 minutes.
About a 4x change.
This AX case,
if you didn't use it alone,
if you didn't switch to this workflow and did it the existing way,
working 12 hours a day
for 2 weeks,
it would take 120 hours, but using this
you can somehow get away with it.
So everyone used it.
Ultimately, the efficiency I always thought about
was that 10x or 20x, I will definitely switch.
4x or 5x is not even close.
That's what I thought.
So why did it succeed?
The pain size was large,
I did it better AI-Native,
and at that time
communication costs were high,
but this worked well because I did it alone?
Also, interestingly,
looking at domain size,
I used proposals much more, and skill consulting
was less,
and at this time, looking at the tech stack, I used it
more heavily. At that time, I only used GPTs.
Leadership drive
was both driven by me,
so these individual
components written down,
this whole thing lacks
explanatory power to explain why success and failure,
and it feels unsettling.
What really
flashed through my mind
was that ultimately it's no different from entrepreneurship.
I reached that thought.
So
first, the key is
if you think carefully about the first commonality
between AX and software startups,
ultimately you succeed only when you make customers
use your new product.
That means customers
have to overcome the switching cost
of switching from existing products to new products.
So now, as Ben Horowitz said,
either make a 10x product
or they won't switch.
In Zero to One as well,
this utility of 10x
kept staying in my head.
Ultimately, it has to be that level
to overcome that switching cost. It's very similar to startups?
That's what I thought.
Ultimately, whether it's a startup or AX,
from the perspective that you have to give customers
a product that creates 10x utility,
you can apply the startup
framework almost identically.
When going for market in startups,
what do they mainly talk about?
It's important to absolutely choose a big market.
They talk about small markets,
but what is a market in AX?
What is it?
It's time.
That time is actually
the sizes of time spent
by organization and workflow category,
each different time is a different market.
Those times are the market size.
Ultimately, to succeed with limited resources
and maintain authority
from my leadership,
you have to choose a market with large transformational size.
Like doing a startup.
So in startups, they always talk about MVP,
and naturally we
go through PoC and scale up.
That's how we're doing AX,
and it seems like a natural approach.
And
in startups, they talk a lot about finding PMF.
They say you've found PMF
only when customers actually pay money.
What does finding PMF mean in AX?
It's not just
"I tried it and it's good,"
but reaching a PoC level where you can't go back
to the original way.
And from a product marketing
perspective,
the customers are the organization members
who use my product.
These are laggards.
Customers who know nothing about AI,
the marketing team.
They don't care about that.
I fit the pieces to match people
and design the user flow
so that just thinking leads naturally to the end.
You have to make it to that level
so they can't go back to the original way. That's finding PMF.
There are also investors.
In startups, naturally,
if VCs who invest when you prove cash are investors,
in AX,
who are the investors?
Upper decision-makers.
While I'm being invested in,
I have to prove ROI
for the resources I've consumed,
so upper decision-makers
will invest more in me.
There's also runway. In startups, when cash runs out, it's bankruptcy.
For the AX team,
what is runway organizational bankruptcy?
Trust.
Ultimately,
when trust from upper decision-makers hits rock bottom,
it's just bankruptcy.
Your authority gets confiscated.
In terms of difficulty, everyone knows
succeeding in a startup is incredibly difficult,
but actually I see AX as the same difficulty level.
Honestly, it's better to start a company than succeed at this.
At least you'd have money.
This has no money,
it's difficult, it's hard.
It's this level of difficulty.
Looking at it that way,
many people ask
why after doing PoC,
the next step doesn't go well.
It's an obvious thing to say. Naturally, you made an MVP,
but the tasks you need to do next
are as packed as in a startup.
AX is no different. PoC is when the real work
begins, so naturally,
PoC success absolutely doesn't
guarantee AX success.
From that perspective, if AX builders
are the same as entrepreneurs,
what combination of capabilities
is needed to succeed in AX?
Today we have Echo and
Delta meeting,
so there's Delta and Echo.
What I think is you need additional
capabilities beyond this. What is it?
The capabilities of PO and PM
all need to be combined to be truly
AX full-stack,
that's what I think. As a consultant,
the capability is naturally logic,
quickly breaking down problems,
structuring bottlenecks, establishing angles,
and iterating logic. But importantly,
you have to do it really fast.
As soon as you hear it, it breaks down, goes all the way, logic comes out,
you run it through agents,
and if results don't come out well, you come back.
You have to be able to do this really fast
to have capability as an AX consultant.
Naturally, you also need capability
as a PO.
What kind of being are humans? You need to know how lazy they are
and how much they dislike things.
You need to have a sense for products
that people use,
and concepts about iteration,
and obsession about problems
to succeed again. I
learned a lot about this at doeat.
Anyway, you need capability
as a PO with this kind of obsession.
You also need PM. Ultimately,
you have to persuade
uncooperative counterparties while doing AX.
My leadership
doesn't give much time,
so before hitting bottom, you have to pull the plane up,
managing schedules,
recovering while doing PoC and succeeding,
then the main project.
You need this capability as a PM.
Actually, there's no difference
from entrepreneurs. It's better to start a company.
At least you'd have money.
Anyway,
so then
thanks to that, when I thought about what
mindset to have when doing AX,
entrepreneurs think like this: nothing is
impossible in the world. I just couldn't find it. But
now we think it's impossible for AI,
and I just instructed it wrong.
Having that mindset
and doing it persistently
is how you succeed. That's the capability set
that's needed, I think.
So there are 3 playbooks
I want to talk about today.
First,
trying thin but end-to-end
makes it easier to quickly create PMF.
That's the first. Now interpreting with the startup
framework,
there's always a gap between expectation and reality,
and as a business person, I really
have to do this. At first,
when I visualized the workflow non-realistically,
everyone will follow this workflow
properly at the organizational level, but
that's absolutely not the case. Everyone
actually has their own workflow.
So after interviewing in more detail
and drawing charts, the workflows
for making proposals, everyone does it the same,
but they all look different. Actually,
because common denominators are absent,
any bottleneck in the workflow,
targeting a specific section,
is actually very difficult to succeed at.
So there's the approach of being thick
and doing part properly,
and from the perspective of trying thin but all the way to the end,
I think the right side is better.
Partially,
actually defining a certain section
as a bottleneck and doing AS
is actually targeting
some interviewees' bottleneck,
their real intersection,
so you're more likely to target
only a smaller market.
It doesn't become organizational AS.
But what we can trust about end-to-end
is this. It's not trusting the workflow,
but ultimately anyway,
workflows have inputs and outputs.
And everyone has to use
the same input in their own way
to make the same final output,
a proposal.
So when approaching end-to-end, organizational-level
AS is more likely. This is the truth.
This is actually not the truth.
And
second, if you choose even edge cases
and go thick and deep,
there's a very high possibility
of folding without even shipping MVP.
Because
a month passes and you're not dead.
Anyway,
so you made money.
What happened? They ask like that,
so in that sense, going thin
allows iteration loops to run really fast,
and there's a higher possibility
of discovering real problems there,
I think.
Going thin but end-to-end
was the first rule I learned. The second is
making it AI-Native from the beginning
makes it a bit easier to 10x.
I think Elon Musk's
thinking is also valid for AX.
Decompose complex problems
to the most basic, fundamental level.
That kind of thinking.
Rockets are too expensive to make
at that price. But what are rockets
made of? The raw materials are like this?
They're not even expensive? Ultimately, what are the
fundamental costs needed for rocket manufacturing?
Digging into that,
similarly, when doing AX in an organization,
there's a lot of work, many tasks,
it's hard. When you hear that,
rather than just believing it
and looking at that workflow exactly,
ultimately
since we're doing intellectual labor,
all our activities are about taking low-value information
and making it into high-value information.
That's all activities.
During the industrial revolution,
we escaped physical labor.
Looking at it that way, ultimately creating
high-value information, all those acts
are what we do.
Let's break down the process
where information value increases. When doing that,
if it's not people doing it but we entrust it to agents,
how many tasks can we eliminate?
Erase all those,
and then partially automating the AX part
is much better.
Rather than starting with human workflow,
trust only the output
and output of the work,
thinking about entrusting it to agents,
questioning the tasks
that people did as natural tasks,
and going AI-Native
by simply erasing everything
makes creating 10x much easier.
That's the second point. The last is
you have to become AX full-stack.
Because ultimately,
before cash, before runway
all gets fixed,
before the balance of trust and
patience runs out,
to succeed, you ultimately need speed.
So
when they gave you time and a month passed, when they ask "what happened?"
some effect has to come out or transformation
has to happen to keep making investment
from the CEO.
Looking at it, ultimately,
from an AX perspective,
you have to be full-stack to succeed.
I'm only thinking about our organization.
In my case,
I'm Echo but to become Delta,
I'm trying Protex,
just like those of you
attending today,
there were many people
in frontend roles.
Frontend-focused engineer
developers need to be Delta to Echo,
continuously expanding capabilities and skillsets
to become full-stack,
to gain speed and succeed.
That's my final conclusion.
Thank you.