Hello
Yes, I'm a bit nervous. I'm Donghoon Lee, leading the AI Lab team at Myrealtrip.
Let me briefly introduce myself. I was an engineer
I was an infrastructure engineer. I wrote 10 years, but it wasn't quite 10 years. For the past 7 years, I worked on monitoring
systems, CI/CD, container environments, and various tasks like DevOps, DBA, SRE
I did all sorts of things. I was basically a jack-of-all-trades.
But as I watched my seniors doing the same work, I really felt
Why do we keep reinventing the wheel when it already exists in the market?
They kept reinventing the wheel and then got crushed by it and quit.
So I felt very strongly in the company that I shouldn't be like that.
There are so many things already available in the market. I just need to assemble them. I decided not to become an inventor.
I think I started thinking that way back then.
Then I encountered GPT-3, and I think I was thinking a lot like this at that time.
It was about 2 years ago.
Back then, our platform team of about 6 people was serving about 1,000
engineers.
That's really tough. Developing software and maintaining systems is already hard, but
we had to handle all kinds of requests.
Even though we built the systems, the questions were so diverse
and those 1,000 developers were very creative in developing and deploying software.
I had to continuously provide guidance for those situations, and even with great documentation
it wasn't easy to find and provide the right information.
So I couldn't work during the day or evening. I could only work at dawn and on weekends
I was thinking about how to solve this, and when I met GPT-3, it felt like I saw the light.
That's when RAG existed, so it was a bit like that for me.
And so I built several RAG-based chatbots using various internal data sources
and based on that, when leadership decided we needed AI transformation
I was able to lead this organization.
So that's how it happened.
We wrote our mission statement like this. Actually, it's not super meaningful.
But the most important thing is raising AI literacy for all employees.
And I don't think we've reached the red text below yet. I think we're mostly focused on raising literacy.
So we're doing these things to raise literacy, though some we're not doing anymore.
Mainly, we hold internal case-sharing sessions every week.
I'll explain later, but we do weekly presentations in "Everyone AI" sessions.
To make that happen, we go hunting for cases every week. When someone uses it well, we share and give awards
When there's a team like that, I immediately go interview them, have them present, and give them money. So far
we've had over 40 presentations.
Some presentations introduced more than two cases.
So the number is a bit more than that.
And we briefly ran a program called Myrealtrip Kmong.
Similar to what we're doing now, like today's presentation topic, we connected people who define problems with people who solve them
It was like a matchmaking platform. We launched five projects
And lastly, what we're doing now is the AI Champion Training Program.
I felt many limitations in connecting core and delta, so now
you solve your own problems.
And we provide a different level of support than before.
I'll explain this more later.
So how we've been working and what lessons we learned
We've had many failures too.
So I'll explain that through about 4 scenes.
I've been on this team for 1 year and 1 month now.
Last November, I started working concurrently on the SRE team and AI Lab.
So I just thought I'd do what I always did - build software and deliver it.
I'm a developer, so naturally I learned LangChain and LangGraph, so let me find problems I can solve with this.
I approached it quite clumsily.
Looking back now.
But there were about 5 business divisions at the time.
So I met with each division head to listen to their inconveniences and unsolved problems
And then we launched three things: a chatbot platform, a keyword extraction engine for SEO, and review translation
A review translation system. We launched these 3 and ran them for about 2 months.
And then we just threw away all the projects.
Threw them in the trash. Actually, even before those 2 months ended, I had a bad feeling
about it.
For example, with SEO, the marketing team responsible for traffic should obviously have ownership
but the marketing team didn't come to me.
I'm not sure why that was.
So I was working on things that weren't important.
From a business perspective.
What I want to talk about here is that the counterpart I was working with
would meet with me weekly for sync-ups like homework, getting assignments, but it didn't seem important to them and they didn't know
what the return would be, so even I could feel it wasn't going well.
So I thought I needed to report the situation quickly somehow
I wrote very detailed wikis every week about goals and current situation, and kept reporting to my PO and CEO.
After doing that for about two months, I think they also realized that this wasn't working.
So we decided to set up the roadmap again, and in a way, I could be delta
but I couldn't be echo.
I'm not someone with great business sense or a strategist.
I might be good at implementation. That's what I felt.
So let's start from scratch again. Literacy came up again at that time
and we decided to pivot to education.
It was really confusing.
I was a coder, and I didn't think I knew enough to teach anyone.
This was around February this year.
There was a lot of interest in developing and tuning models.
I don't have a machine learning background, so what can I teach?
What can I show people?
I was in that kind of vague state.
But anyway, I couldn't not start.
So I decided to just start, and I started with how to use ChatGPT.
What I said during that ChatGPT usage session is so embarrassing now
When evaluating team members, export all Jira tickets and give them to ChatGPT 3.5
and have it summarize what this person did. That level.
And small tips like how to write formulas in Google Sheets. I started with those little things.
I shared things like that. And at that time, I was
deeply interested in developing RAG systems based on AI.
Anyway, I was continuously learning about building agent systems, so I thought
I should teach some of this too, and I looked for people who could teach it.
I even contacted a YouTuber and got quotes, but I couldn't convince management
to go that far.
In the end, it was really good that case studies had much more power than knowing how-to.
Telling my story is good, and when colleagues around me are facing similar problems
and solving them, people gain confidence and think "I can do this too"
and take on challenges.
Seeing that, I was surprised too, and I felt that this was much more effective
than taking lectures.
That's right. So even though I initially planted a weak idea
some people tried first. As I saw these attempts succeed, from that point
other people started asking me questions, but not just "I asked ChatGPT and it didn't work"
They succeeded at the first step of "I think I can do something"
and failed at the second step.
So when I showed them methods and they solved it, it gave me much more sense of efficacy
I think.
After that, this happened. As cases kept being created and shared, at that time
what we were mainly doing was developing Chrome extensions or automating operations in Google Apps Script
with Google Sheets or Google Docs.
As you know, there's not that much you can do.
In that situation, people wanted to go further.
They wanted to automate the entire workflow, but when they asked ChatGPT, it said "Learn Python, learn TypeScript"
"Run Node.js" - people were getting guidance like that.
But these non-developers came to me asking "How do I do Python?"
"My head is going to explode."
"What should I do? Please teach me."
These kinds of inquiries started coming in, and I wondered, is it right to make these people do this?
What should I do?
Just saying "you can do it" didn't seem like enough. I thought about that a lot.
So I thought, let's connect them with developers, and that's how
Myrealtrip Kmong started.
Actually, with Myrealtrip Kmong at first, I approached this work thinking I needed to build a software system
and I said I'd do it in a month, but then I wasted a month.
That's what happened.
I'll explain the lesson a bit more later.
But Myrealtrip Kmong launched 5 projects and then we just closed it.
Actually, even running Myrealtrip Kmong was really difficult.
Because we had to connect business experts with development experts, but developers don't understand the business
so they obviously can't solve their problems. To raise their understanding to that level required a lot of interviews and analysis.
And this was basically a bidding competition program, so when 2 or more people applied, we had to select one
That's how the program was structured.
So an unspecified number of people had to understand the business.
So I spent almost a week just interviewing and taking screenshots.
That was difficult, but the real problem was after all the software was delivered.
Maintenance was the issue.
These people paid a service fee and received delivered software.
In that state, when maintenance issues arose, they couldn't solve them.
They don't know Python, so how can they fix a Python program they received?
That situation happened.
And quite emptily, the developers kept solving those maintenance issues.
But they had no motivation at all.
They briefly worked on things that didn't align with their goals at all.
Actually, the reason they could do it was the prize money.
It was all about the prize money, and once the one-time prize was paid, the problem solvers
didn't really need to maintain it actively.
That's how it was.
And as I said, since it wasn't their business or goal, no matter how hard they worked on it
it wouldn't reflect in their performance.
So I felt again at that time.
People must solve their own problems.
But thankfully at that time
we have a finance and accounting team.
The team leader, who had never done software development or engineering
built a Qt-based desktop standalone application in Python to automate their work
automating Excel manual work.
Beyond doing it themselves, they assigned team members "do this, do that" and made them present weekly.
I didn't know, actually.
That person is now a member of our team.
Seeing that gave me courage too.
With Cursor's features improving, it became possible.
The world was changing so much.
So from then on, non-developers can do everything.
They can make web services, Chrome extensions, standalone applications - they can make everything
I gained that confidence then and closed Myrealtrip Kmong.
So the program we started again
is the AI Champion Training Program.
As we wrote, the core principle is solving your own problems.
And this program was initially run very ad-hoc.
People would say "I want to do this" and come join, things like that.
As we gradually established a framework, I thought about what program we could benchmark
and thought Y Combinator's batch program was somewhat similar.
Except for investment, their mentoring program seems similar to ours.
We run it in batches.
So how we work now is - I couldn't really put photos here but
we open office hours for 2 hours a day, and people working on projects can come anytime within those 2 hours.
Our team member acts as a tutor and is present, and we sync up with each person who comes about their current situation
what problems they're facing, and we just try to solve it together for about 30 minutes.
If they gain knowledge or if I can prove that something is possible, they take it back
and try it themselves.
We're doing a lot of these things, and among the completed projects
let me introduce a few. A designer made a Figma plugin to create advertising materials
It was originally an animation but you can't see it now, but when you run the plugin
a modal window pops up like that.
If you input some parameters there, since we're a travel company, for travel promotion materials
it renders each card that goes on the promotion page. So when you input a product ID
it extracts the properties, how should I put it.
For example, if it's a hotel.
It randomly picks a few hotel room photos or pool photos and fills them as card content, and for the hotel's
detailed information text, it sends a call to the Anthropic API and
generates hooking phrases, and fills different card types - horizontal, vertical, square
with these templates to generate them instantly. That's the plugin they made.
The second one is also advertising.
They made a back office web application for their business like that, and
made the company's official homepage, and a marketer made an airline price comparison site
to increase traffic to our flights - they did experiments like that too.
The lessons learned here are about four.
First, in our case-sharing sessions, seeing colleagues next to you succeed and gaining confidence is most important.
Rather than what power tools you can use or how to use them, just having confidence that you can do it is much more
important.
Second, it's best when someone with ownership does this work.
In Myrealtrip Kmong, when someone without ownership solved problems, communication costs were very high and it wasn't
easy to sustain.
Third, we always run with a small team. I started as a team of one, and now
we're 3 people. For a while it was 2 people.
So we're also making a lot of efforts to work AI-natively, and as you can see here, when champions
apply for a batch, we created pre-interviews to get more
specific answers we want.
And finally, start quickly and visualize.
This is two things. Actually, for the Myrealtrip Kmong project, I wasted a month trying to build a system, but after meeting with my leader
we made the first case in 15 minutes and launched immediately.
Ignoring all the system.
Actually, I witnessed my developer clumsiness again
at that moment.
And second, this is about raising literacy, how can we effectively
gain motivation and do this?
What you see here isn't about using coding tools.
It's just calculating how many lines you wrote and creating a ranking.
Like this, we collect all events and work done internally as metrics as much as possible
and enable competition.
And now we're thinking about various things. Initially, I thought we shouldn't develop
but these days, development costs are converging to almost zero, so now it seems worth challenging again
And in a way, the systems we want to build are becoming more sophisticated
and requirements are getting acutely difficult, so I think it would be good to build something. So we're developing agents
And I've been mainly working with non-developers, but the development organization also needs to think about
the next stage much more, and we're continuing to research what the 10x engineer that everyone talks about
looks like and how to define it.
Thank you.