This is my first time sitting and having a talk show like this.
So I hope you enjoy the show,
We have our first question today.
Our first question is,
In today's presentations, we heard a lot about how Echo Delta specifically uses AI well,
The first question is,
Actually, each of you uses AI so well.
So I'm curious from what moment you started using it well.
Because, after all, we're doing work,
And work has inertia.
There are ways I've always worked,
But working with AI means you have to let go of those ways.
So what was that moment like,
I'm curious about that,
And since Seojin is making eye contact right now,
Seojin will react first.
I previously worked at a company called Boors as an AI product engineer,
What was funny was, there was no designer, no frontend engineer, no backend engineer,
I was supposed to develop features alone.
What? They don't give me Figma?
So I met directly with decision-makers to listen,
And had to ship features in a short period,
That's when I first started using it to the max,
Second, as I coded like crazy with AI,
I got scolded a lot in code reviews.
So I didn't want to get scolded anymore.
So, ah, Claude Code produces better results,
That's when I switched to the second code and started using it much more.
Yes, that's right.
Dongun, what about you?
Mine is a bit similar,
Seojin didn't have colleagues to collaborate with.
I think it was a situation where I received an unreasonable request.
Once I was out at an external meetup,
And my boss's boss said to me,
We have many cases, how about writing a blog post?
That's what they said.
I said okay, I'll do it next Monday.
It was Friday then.
I think it was Thursday or Friday.
So you said next Monday?
Can't you do it earlier?
That's how challenges come to me.
So doing that,
I'm at this meetup right now but I need to do something.
And there wasn't just one case back then.
I didn't think they'd ask me to write just one blog.
Instinctively.
So I need to quickly make an agent that can mass-produce blogs.
I had all the transcribed scripts anyway.
So I went to that meetup,
Opened Anthropic Workbench,
Did about 19 steps,
That agent, single agent,
Kept building up the prompt.
Then looked at the output,
Had people review it,
Gave feedback,
When the prompt improved with feedback,
Ran it about 10 times,
Then something came out.
So,
On Friday, I just churned out 3 blog posts,
About 70-point blogs
I remember writing like that.
So we,
The blogs we saw,
Human,
Ah,
There was some final touch,
But actually,
Almost like that.
It's a speed humans can't achieve.
I really relate to that,
I also use Claude Code,
What's called multi-Clauding,
Opening multiple sessions,
Running features across worktrees,
Making things while wondering what they are,
That process,
I first did when I received an unreasonable request.
Really.
At the company I was working for then,
A new vice president joined,
The vice president called me,
Hey, go next week,
And present to the client.
Ah, I'm presenting?
Then who's making it?
Hey, I'm the one making it.
If I make it, I have to present it,
With 3 days left.
That's when it was really intense,
That's when something,
Felt like a point of no return.
I felt that too,
Geonho, what about you?
Very similar,
Experience,
I also found it interesting while listening,
Uh,
Constraints create innovative thinking.
I think.
For me now,
This event happened during my probation period,
Actually,
Starting out,
Ah, I want to execute. I want to join a startup.
I had gathered all my vacation days,
So I had exactly one week
To go through the probation period.
But now,
To pass,
One more experiment needed to be done within a week,
And then,
Run SQL queries,
Do BA,
Complete all the analysis,
All within a week,
I only knew SELECT FROM WHERE,
At that level,
Suddenly had to join all sorts of tables,
What, calculate delivery time and what,
Had to calculate retention,
So for me it was like,
Make a computer in a week without a calculator,
That's what it felt like,
That's when I had a wow moment.
So it was GPT 3.5 back then,
Actually not good at reasoning, but anyway,
For queries,
The performance was already incredible,
Of course it's close to coding,
That's when I felt wow,
And then started
Following up more seriously.
On AI technology.
Naturally.
My presentation content is actually,
About that.
Right.
Just,
If you do work you can't do without AI,
You'll use it. That's really true.
If you do work you can do without AI,
People don't use it.
I think so.
I've worked closely with
The design team,
So there's an interesting case
I'd like you to share,
When the designer,
Was seeking,
And made something while watching,
Please tell us more about that.
That's similar too. If you don't let them use Figma,
They work like that. Really.
If you say you've done everything,
And there's no time to use Figma,
And they say they won't do it,
That makes a big difference.
So,
Perks at the end of the year, you know.
Now we,
Since we use Claude Code perks together,
There were no talks but,
Our designer,
Was in the top 44% worldwide.
A designer, but beat 56%
Of developers worldwide.
For design systems and such,
No need for Figma.
They put everything in code,
Everything. Anyway, if you open the build and look,
That's the truth.
Like Storybook.
If you don't buy Figma,
No time to use Figma.
Figma stock might not do well.
I think so.
If you try Figma to code,
Not everything in Figma is in the code.
What really surprised me,
Just now,
The case I asked about,
During a sync we were having,
That time, the designer
Brought a mockup.
But this was almost just,
Actually working.
So, huh? Did you,
Develop this directly in code?
I thought,
But when I looked at the screen, it was Google AI Studio.
Google AI Studio,
But it looked exactly like our actual popup service.
The appearance.
So I asked how they did it,
Used Cursor to extract CSS and,
Index files and all that,
Put it in AI Studio like that,
And it came out looking exactly the same,
And the designer,
Added buttons like this and this,
Then next screen should go like this.
Made all the screens,
And they all worked.
So I just looked at that,
Synced, and went straight to development.
So fresh,
So fun.
Connecting a bit,
I also have a case that comes to mind,
This, in a way,
In an organization,
This could work,
If you confiscate calculators,
Anyway, it's a bit closer to code,
And they've heard of Claude Code,
But for me,
For non-developer organizations,
Sales teams, education consultant teams,
Teams that work hard on PPTs,
And meet customers,
I tried various things,
My style is also pretty strong,
So at first I wanted to confiscate,
Something,
But first the target isn't very clear.
So if you confiscate PPT,
Will they use Canva?
It almost doesn't become like that.
Sales, SaaS, tools we're using,
If you confiscate that, will they make dashboards directly?
For such non-developers,
It's hard to clearly calculate BAT,
That's the difficult point.
Second,
As I mentioned before
In distribution,
This is general,
In other job functions,
Should I call it familiarity?
More than you think,
There's a bigger gap than we think,
What shocked me was,
I,
Run deep search,
Then make a storyline for the proposal,
Make a GPT,
Create proposal content,
Keep using it like this,
So I should train this internally,
I thought.
Did internal training,
Wrote the prompt framework almost on the board.
It's not difficult.
Just write as on the board.
Before pressing enter,
Each person leave your prompt on Slack
As a comment.
Gave them 5 minutes,
No one left Slack comments.
Don't be shy,
Just write what you don't know as is.
Look at that and ride along.
But no one ran it,
So I went around,
The meeting room.
But some people,
Were frozen.
Couldn't write one sentence.
But I was shocked.
Just write what's on the board as is.
From Google, from Naver,
Just copy-paste 3 KT new technology articles.
But there,
They stopped,
I had many thoughts.
And somewhat,
The confiscation method,
Could be big trouble,
I thought.
For non-developer organizations,
I think that's the result.
Such a good story.
Then,
Since confiscation is a bit harsh,
Before the next question,
You two seem to be getting too much light,
Shall we sit a bit forward?
Saved your eyesight.
Confiscation,
Is a harsh term,
So changing to the word unlearn,
A bit,
To work well with AI,
Specifically,
What skillsets or,
What mindsets should we unlearn?
And,
Conversely, things good to learn,
Things we must learn,
What are they?
What does each of you think,
Well,
To put it briefly,
There's nothing it can't do,
But,
It's just that I can't make it do it,
That mindset,
I think we should make all media have it,
But how that gets learned,
How that mindset is built,
I don't really know,
I set up an AX team,
We just matched
Smart people,
They don't know n8n, don't know anything.
But, on LinkedIn,
n8n workflows,
About 6,000 cases in JSON
Were uploaded on GitHub,
So I said,
Let's use this later.
If it were me, I would have done it like this.
I did it like this,
But that person doesn't know Python,
Asked GPT,
How do I extract all JSONs from a folder?
Python code came out.
Then the question was, I don't know Python.
Tell me how to do it on Windows.
So,
I don't know if PowerShell was suggested,
Extracted all JSONs from folders,
Read the text in them,
Through GPT extracted
Workflows worth referencing,
Let's reference these 6 for our project.
Brought those words.
I was shocked then.
This mindset,
Is the starting point.
Shall we go in order?
Shall I go?
That result earlier,
That story really resonated,
Thinking only result-oriented,
Is necessary.
Forget all about the process,
For example, if we're climbing a mountain,
The path humans take and the path AI takes are different.
I've found.
It's felt a lot.
So need to reach the summit,
Need to reach basecamp in the middle,
Just mark a few points,
Better to forget all the paths, I think.
And what needs to be learned,
Result-oriented thinking.
Mark only results accurately,
The process,
The workflow I knew,
Anyway,
As shown earlier,
Everyone is different.
And my method isn't the answer,
There's always a better method,
And I won't be doing that,
So do it the way I'm good at, often,
Mark results accurately,
Forget all processes.
And what needs to be learned is result-oriented,
How to specify results,
Understanding what my desires are, what I want,
I think these are important.
If I talk about our company case,
It might be helpful,
What should we unlearn?
From that perspective,
Our company is,
Running a program called job expansion.
A kind of product engineer
Cultivation program,
I also tried backend development,
Frontend development a bit,
Android development,
These things for about a week,
Complete a bootcamp-like thing,
Actual Android tickets come in,
Work on those tasks,
Can do these,
Haven't tried yet.
But actually running these programs,
iOS developers
Doing backend development,
Sending PRs,
And backend developers
Doing frontend development,
Sending PRs, doing these things.
But previously,
Frontend specific modules,
Functional organizations developing specific screens,
Receiving PRs,
Extremely low quality,
Shouldn't be used,
Plastered with,
PRs being sent,
PR comments
130, 140,
So they came to me from there.
This doesn't match code conventions,
Anti-pattern,
No need for such complex algorithm,
Things like this.
But I think
We need some meta-cognition about that.
Do result-oriented thinking,
What's the bottleneck there,
You yourself need to
Recognize a bit,
That's probably the point of unlearning,
The point where unlearning should happen,
I thought.
Of course,
Me doing it,
And making others do it,
Are really different parts.
And, what needs to be learned,
I actually have that too.
I try my best
Not to be a bottleneck,
Wanting to work like
100x, 1000x superman,
But I also can't let go,
Because of that,
I feel I'm becoming a bottleneck a lot.
So if I want to
Do more here,
What should I do,
Actually it's a bit similar perspective.
What to let go,
Then things to learn emerge.
I'm focusing much more
On unlearning.
In that sense.
My thinking is similar,
Ultimately why,
Can't we unlearn,
If you think about it,
The development speed of tools
Wasn't that fast,
Under that premise,
Continuously using these tools
The same way to get familiar,
Ultimately became better
At using the tools,
So people didn't switch tools
That quickly.
But, ultimately letting go of that
Tool-using inertia,
Continuously when new things
Come out,
Having the habit of experimenting,
Rather,
Letting go of that habit,
And trying,
Should be learned,
I thought.
Really resonate,
This morning,
I,
Sent text messages
To everyone coming today.
How did I do it at home,
To Gemini,
Hey, mass send text messages,
All at once,
But, if sent as group message,
Recipients shouldn't know each other.
Asked how to do it,
With MacBook shortcuts and,
Contacts and such,
Made some workflow,
Said it would send one by one.
I tried it,
But it didn't work. I tested,
It just sent as group chat.
So frustrated,
Next meeting no time,
So just asked Claude Code,
Hey, right now,
Today's meetup day,
I had the CSV list.
Can you,
Send text messages?
As soon as I asked,
I wrote Apps Script completely,
And sent it right away.
So,
I realized again today.
Ah, just from the beginning,
I'll ask Claude Code.
Not just ask,
I'll ask it to do it.
I'll whine about it.
I thought like this,
And realized once again.
This is really powerful.
Prompting is really powerful.
I came to think.
Probably even this,
Screen turning off issue,
I asked Claude Code.
Really Claude Code is all you need,
I really often think.
AI is greatly,
Advancing,
But Claude Code tool itself is also,
So good,
AI models keep getting better,
As you mentioned,
Tools themselves are also tremendously
Improving in performance,
I'm just curious about these things.
Personally,
I use this tool
To this extreme extent.
I'm pretty good at this.
Stories like this,
I'm curious,
Seojin,
Do you have a story to share?
What I know,
People who really use Claude Code well,
There are so many.
What can I talk about?
I think everyone's similar.
So obviously,
Deployment or,
Development-related,
Most things,
All done with Claude Code,
And preparing today's presentation,
On the way here,
Wanted to receive script or expected Q&A,
So,
Wrote Q&A about my Claude Code system,
Sent it by email to receive,
Actually there's that.
I do UI, UX,
Design generation itself
Through Claude Code,
But,
How did I design the function called generate design,
I asked,
Like Figma to code
Agents,
Your design generation
Iterative process and,
Feedback loop parameters,
Prompted to tell me,
Implemented that as function,
Then Gemini is best
At design generation,
So with Gemini CLI or,
Gemini API do design generation,
Designing.
I'm designing like that.
Expert,
Hacking,
As I mentioned,
Doing hacking.
One more thing,
Trying hard to speak,
While not listening,
Wanting to do panel talk well,
I'm trying to share
Some cases,
I'm an AX consultant,
As Echo,
How do I use it,
I use Codex.
The reason I use it,
I've been paying for GPT Pro,
So more token quota,
I'm using Codex,
Ultimately analyzing customers,
Writing proposals,
Or when needing new logic,
Ultimately,
Claude Code has something called skills,
You use that.
But,
Ultimately for me,
All work tacit knowledge existing in the world,
For non-developer jobs,
All work tacit knowledge can actually be
Made as sentences, as explicit knowledge,
Actually that explicit knowledge is all in
LLMs,
So even if I'm not a marketer,
Not a content marketer,
As an LLM developer,
Even not knowing how pretty to make this web,
Ultimately running deep search,
Skillsets formalized as explicit knowledge
All contained and come out.
So I,
When needing to do some work,
Deep search,
Open about 20 GPT tabs,
For work I need to do,
Knowledge sets that might be needed,
For those,
Create research content.
Run about 20 deep searches.
While running about 20,
Need to start work,
As consultant, knowledge needed for problems,
Roughly from here to here if we collect all,
It's all contained,
Get the sense roughly,
Extract all as explicit knowledge,
Connect all to GPT or Gems'
Knowledge,
With all this knowledge,
Let's create first logic,
Start problem-solving.
Rather than thinking with my head,
Thinking with my head to
Create logic,
Tacit knowledge I don't know,
Not through interviews,
Using deep search like McKinsey feeling,
Utilizing.
So my wife is shocked.
Stop using GPT so much,
20 Chrome tabs,
20 GPT,
20 Gemini tabs,
40, 15,
Running like that,
So my wife just,
Anyone else?
Need to do each one.
Not knowing McKinsey,
We use Cursor a lot,
The reason we use Cursor,
We,
Working under time pressure,
Actually Cursor with Claude Agent and,
Then in Slack,
Made Slack bot,
Before Claude Code.
Going back and forth,
Ultimately in Slack mentioning Cursor,
Making it work,
Is so good,
As you saw, what we do.
Just @Cursor do this,
So much becomes done,
Slack thread takes context as is and brings it,
We McDonaldized it,
Made a guide,
Anyway people tell it what they'd tell it as is,
If you look at our Slack channel,
@Cursor and,
It's all on Slack.
That probably,
Hearing other stories,
That's one reason we can't go to Claude Code.
But earlier we did McDonald's menu,
Menu actually,
After making menus,
Next month Claude Code skills came out.
Very similar actually, the perspective itself.
Claude Code skills guide,
Skills making guide,
Brought our menu guide as is,
McDonald's menu making guide is actually Claude Code skills.
So now,
Almost one-to-one correspondence,
Those things are,
We worked hard.
Since such people exist,
Claude probably got inspired, I also thought.
But what we use most,
Cursor, daytime and weekends,
@Cursor please do,
Especially since we work with US,
US team members
Say something in English.
There @Cursor,
Fix this,
That's the best.
Earlier everyone was using so well,
I just,
Cutely,
How I use it,
Will briefly tell you,
For me now making
Presentation materials is very,
Stressful.
Not me making presentation materials,
Making others make presentation materials is stressful.
Usually,
With developers,
And designers,
Slide quality,
Is very obviously different.
Developers really only have text.
But this needs to be imported.
That's so stressful.
So these days how I do it,
First our,
Mockup program or training,
When cases come out,
First schedule 30-minute interview.
Even if offline meeting face-to-face,
Must Google Meet,
Join please turn on mic.
Join, transcribe, record.
Take transcribed script as is,
Send to Claude PT,
Gamma receives well,
There's a format.
Slide content,
Just pick sentences,
And between slides,
Just separate with 3 dashes,
Then now,
That becomes separated as
Plain text for one slide.
Just wrap that in code block,
Ask to extract one,
Those slides,
Just copyable form,
Come out as code block.
Copy that as is,
To Gamma make from plain text.
Then now paste,
Just generate,
Slides I want come out as is,
Then now after 30-minute meeting,
I roughly,
Did so many such meetings,
Roughly what flow of questions,
Need to extract I know.
Ask questions well, receive answers well,
And with that,
About 10 minutes after meeting ends,
Slides come out.
Doing it like that.
Using so well.
I'll also brag one thing,
This is a pattern I discovered
While looking at screen with Seojin,
Also saw Jonghyeon's pattern,
Some,
Development,
Projects,
So multiple repositories get created.
Multiple repositories created,
Put these as submodules,
Put them,
Make upper repository and use it.
What this means,
Each development project,
Or something shared,
Archiving repository,
All good,
Wrap all this,
Contexts wrapping all this clearly exist.
For example,
In our team,
Our team,
Our team uses these words.
Our team members are these people.
Our mission is this,
OKRs are this,
All sorts of projects we're doing are these projects,
Decision records so far are these things,
As MD file just,
As repository,
Manage as file system.
Beneath that,
Make projects folder,
Put all development projects or,
Open source projects.
And Claude Code,
At the very top,
Turn it on here,
All context known here,
With ability to know all, downward,
Spread Claude Code.
So now,
That homepage displayed,
Just separately,
Without putting in projects,
Just the homepage I want to make,
For,
Tell some style,
Who our team members are,
Who each one is,
Make it.
Deploy to Vercel.
Deployed at once.
That kind of,
Context,
Extreme usage patterns,
I really,
Myself very,
Thought this is something,
But Seojin hyung was already doing it,
This something is really a pattern,
I think,
Think proudly of this,
So far we,
Had some talk.
Originally tried to do
4 questions like this,
Time flowed more fun,
Continuing right away,
Let's hear
Questions directly.
I'll slightly,
Probably,
Questions,
Were written,
I wonder.
If there are definitely questions.
Questions then,
From here a bit,
So many?
Touching.
This last night,
Geontae made quickly,
I gave Geontae simple,
Requirements prompt,
And human,
Made it.
This also our team,
Made right inside wrapper,
Anyway,
Seojin, most
Likes received,
In actual automated AI workflows,
Where were points where
Human evaluation or intervention entered,
Humans still need to
Enter in middle,
When were moments judged,
Curious.
This question,
Exactly where,
Seojin is using,
Why judged so, curious.
That question,
Received most likes.
First previously,
I don't intervene,
Premise system,
Was attached.
But, anyway,
That system being good,
Diplomatically human,
Reviews,
First,
I lack
Domain knowledge.
In development process,
Not sure if that's the question,
Marketing variations,
Producing,
After executing marketing,
Why this variation had good results,
Why this variation,
Why didn't this campaign work well?
Like,
Extracting insights qualitatively,
Must be with domain experts,
Together,
Review results.
I lack domain knowledge,
Can't extract proper insights in parts,
First,
Must have humans enter,
Placed.
I actually mostly,
Don't look in middle.
Look at results,
Modify,
A bit more,
Will think about it.
Next also,
Most likes received,
Seojin's question.
Continuing, simply,
Until creating builder and marketer,
What learning process and,
References were there,
Trial and error question.
How could such sophisticated agent,
Be made.
This is a bit embarrassing,
Continuously,
Intentionally,
Must humans do this?
Repeat finding references,
Why must I do this?
From that perspective,
Repeating all work,
It became like that.
In that process,
Anyway,
Actually,
That workflow,
Like myself,
When working feels best.
When designed like that,
Results in middle,
Why didn't it work well?
Why did this skill,
I told it to check this part,
Why did it pass the gate?
Doubts arise sometimes.
Now,
Must,
Skills in middle,
Make them tool-call,
Tool-call results and,
Function contents all logged,
LLM,
In batch at once,
Patterns I often said and,
Error patterns that often occurred,
Analyze and modify.
What's the reference,
Workflows I'm working on,
Observe,
Measure,
Enable improvement,
That's the biggest reference.
Observe, measure,
Improve.
I definitely heard somewhere.
Amazing.
So good.
Donghoon also has next question.
Practitioners,
Those who utilize AI well,
Selecting,
Direct problem-solving seems
Currently best,
In selecting practitioners,
Ultimately AI,
Personas who utilize well,
Selecting,
People who use AI well,
Or,
Earning rewards to encourage such things,
Continuing,
Additionally,
Technical support level supporting,
To what extent,
What form,
Curious about that.
Yes.
First,
Making such programs,
Structuring incentives well
Is really important.
But, those who use well,
Even without running such programs,
Use well to create impact,
Gets well announced.
That's what I saw.
What we can prime,
First that incentive has,
Financial rewards too.
My monthly presentation,
Presenting about 500,000 won
Prize attached.
So, like this,
It's designed,
We,
Those who do well,
Of course must attract well,
Others too,
Somewhat, how to say,
We first,
Before starting recruitment,
Start recruiting.
When recruiting,
We made Google form.
Here really detailed,
Write.
But that Google detailed,
Too obvious they can't write themselves.
Making this,
Made one GPT.
So this,
Generally interviewers should have,
Virtues or,
Interviewer skills,
Just extract once.
Made as YAML,
And, our questionnaires,
Extract all,
Said need to make this,
Last instruction,
If you finished questions,
Got all answers,
Make to recoverable level immediately.
Did like this.
Here, how well their workflow,
Organized,
What they want in mind,
Is specified,
And with this can sufficiently create business impact,
Item,
And they have to solve this,
Will or time allocation,
Have such things,
Focused on looking at these.
So like that,
Ultimately we did qualitative evaluation.
Did that,
How we help,
Now we,
Have 3 team members,
15 projects 5 each handling,
Mentoring.
Office hours 2 hours,
About 3 people waiting for me.
Then I now,
30 minutes each,
Work.
This,
Technical some,
What to use to solve this problem.
n8n, Google Apps Script,
Or with Cursor,
Web service development, with Supabase there,
Many recipes, these things,
All made in pre-interview stage.
Almost pre-interview,
Human interview once more.
So now really,
What pictures to draw,
Actually must align with person,
Do that interview once more,
There technically,
What tools to use to make,
That combination we,
First primarily making.
But actually building up,
Something,
Change factors are many.
So, those things,
How do we do then,
Use n8n,
Actually don't know well.
All first-time users,
We were first too.
Then, from Google Spreadsheet extract data,
Give AI some prompt input,
Resulting insight tools,
Feed back to Google Spreadsheet,
Here somehow templating,
Make some slides in Google Slides,
Take that link,
Send email from Google Spreadsheet.
All this can be done with n8n.
Then we, my method is,
Slightly different per team member,
I can get Google Spreadsheet data with n8n.
Show sample.
Put some data in AI,
Can extract some output.
Show this once,
And can put this data in Google Spreadsheet.
Show this,
Can send email. Show,
With what template in Google Slides,
Can produce one slide.
Give those elements,
Now Lego blocks all prepared,
Assemble,
What hyperparameters to put there,
You,
Test.
Doing like this.
Good.
Now I'm not asking
In like order,
There's an interesting question,
So asking,
AX and,
Startups seem really similar.
In that sense,
Becoming AX is difficult,
But business is very clear,
If there's a company,
Rather than fixing it,
How about remaking with AI?
Not fixing,
Looking and making new.
About this,
Curious about panelists' opinions.
That,
There's a client,
Doesn't seem AI native,
When AI native grows bigger,
Rather than changing, isn't it better I start a company,
Seems like this question.
Hear daily.
Startup is startup,
Fixing and,
Looking and making new,
Which is better,
What do you think about this?
Definitely,
tear it down and build new,
that's definitely better.
When I thought about this too,
if this is harder than starting a business,
then starting a business is better, right?
As an individual in this era,
ways to make a lot of money are,
though this is a difficult business,
accomplishing this to capture
more money.
Or,
thinking this feels like a legacy business,
just do it myself then.
I'll start a business,
self-supply,
if there's a vendor like this,
it really feels like a legacy here.
A business supplying desks and equipment
to companies,
here just,
100 people,
if these are typically small-medium businesses,
reducing labor costs drastically to 5 people,
if you just widen the price gap,
ultimately to customers,
the service they see is the same,
but since the price is much cheaper,
could we break in?
That's what you might think,
but I think this is quite dangerous.
I think so too.
Me too,
trying to expand the business in various ways,
while trying new markets,
I've tried for a long time,
what looks like legacy in a certain market,
mid-sized and small companies each holding their position,
they all have reasons.
So, it's not just about price,
that's not it. That customers choose them.
So, things I don't know,
they each hold some edge I don't know about,
these people have been running businesses
sustainably for 10, 20 years,
so these are organizations that have,
simply from AX,
being cheaper, being fancier,
even now,
can't even raise output quality,
the businesses you've seen ultimately,
even with AX, the value delivered to customers is the same,
so there's only price value,
with just price value,
can you penetrate the market?
Well, you have to try to know,
picking one of those,
breaking through well,
succeeding that way,
you could bet on that,
I think the failure probability is quite high.
While trying AX in various businesses,
oh, here AX itself can really
work as an edge,
when you get that feeling about a business,
grabbing a specific vertical,
that's when you start a business,
I think that might be a safer play.
That's great.
I can't not hear from Seojin.
Because Seojin grabbed a vertical,
and is doing it now.
Are you tearing down and building new?
I had nothing to tear down first.
When I was at a company before,
I wanted to tear it down but couldn't.
If you tear it down, you get in trouble.
So I'm building new.
So now,
you're doing AX for brands'
businesses,
that's what you started, right?
When starting,
working with a brand,
respecting their workflow,
VS,
tear it down and build new.
Definitely tear it down.
Definitely tear it down,
if you try to use the former somehow,
it's so frustrating,
growth doesn't happen.
It's easy.
But what's really difficult is,
people using the original workflow,
they want to stick to it.
They want to keep their ways.
Getting them hooked on the show,
seems important.
Anyway, for me,
the conclusion is we need to tear it down,
that's the biggest concern,
and my conclusion is show them first.
Show them while tearing down.
I see.
I have so many questions here,
it's a bit difficult
to go through all of them.
So to capture the feeling
of meeting offline,
from now on,
I'd like to take questions directly.
Whether you wrote questions here
or not, it doesn't matter.
Raise your hand now,
if you have a question,
I'll come to you.
I'll bring the mic.
Hello.
I'm Park Jonghyun.
Following up on the previous question,
I had a question.
People,
are hard to change.
I think tearing down is right.
I spent a year trying to change people,
pushing AX hard,
and saw it not working too many times.
So like you said earlier,
you have to change the people.
Remove all the people,
and create new people.
I've reached this conclusion.
But ultimately,
that's tearing down and building new.
So that kind of,
is my current conclusion.
Big companies,
might have the will,
but will face many challenges,
and companies without that will,
like Seojin, whom I heard about today for the first time,
running a service alone like that,
will inevitably
lose to services like that.
Eventually.
Big companies will face challenges.
That's what I think,
and extending this thought,
organizations as we know them now,
have enormous power,
and people gather,
big synergy?
Creating big value,
but you're making it alone, right?
Organizations,
will organizations of the future,
be able to exist?
Many organizations will disappear,
so how will future organizations look,
I'm curious.
Let me take the lead,
and think about it,
I've been continuously,
increasing our business unit's productivity.
With the keyword AX,
since the CEO isn't curious about it,
anyway,
proposing more,
winning more,
did it make money,
from that perspective,
I think organizations,
why do they survive?
Why do organizations
seem to survive,
I think the source of truth
isn't properly built yet, so organizations
will inevitably survive.
For example, we have
a sales SaaS,
and Slack, and Google Spreadsheets
with planning documents,
and proposals in PPT.
AI can do everything humans can do,
all of it,
but needs to receive all the context I have,
that's what needs to be given,
so what we're doing now is,
creating a source of truth,
so it can all be fed to the AI,
making it,
but that's not easy.
AI can't remember all context at once,
memorizing human people,
to use only when needed at once,
not yet possible,
so when needed, the information needed
has to be accessed,
making something like that,
until that's ready,
people will keep gathering
scattered data sources,
in their heads to consolidate,
they have to keep doing that,
for the proposal due today
to go out today, and tomorrow too.
So DT has to happen first,
that's what I think,
until it's complete,
people are somewhat needed,
honestly, I think that's their lifespan.
I thought exactly the same as Jonghyun.
Thinking the same,
Seojin is the future,
that's it,
I thought,
but what's really interesting is,
with Seojin at the center,
people gather around,
or a better organization
will seek out Seojin,
ultimately something that looks like an organization,
in the past it might not have been called
an organization.
Things that look like organizations,
will form.
And then I,
Cursor recently,
when they got funding,
did a lot of branding about
how they work.
On X,
if you search "First day at Cursor",
with that phrase,
there are lots of photos
that come up,
photos of shoes scattered around,
US startups,
among US and other startups,
there are startups with a culture
of taking off shoes before entering.
Cursor is very representative of that.
So they,
even now,
how do they work,
not that different.
They work quite analog.
What I imagined was,
wouldn't Cursor use Agents most easily?
Then each person,
sitting at their desk,
working from home,
and the rest should work,
they'd get lots of funding too.
Running Agents like crazy,
working that way, I thought,
new feature is out.
Then everyone come to the basement.
So they go to the basement,
to the basement,
to find bugs in the new feature,
they break it. The developers.
Among startups,
one of the places where the smartest people
in the world have gathered
is probably there,
and even there,
they work like a traditional organization,
I see.
So the form might
change,
but people gather
to work together.
That was so interesting.
So hearing Jonghyun's story,
actually even before that,
I thought very similarly,
and wanting to learn,
I contacted Seojin,
with other people,
doing things together,
really in an offline space,
gathering to do something.
That,
I think is really valuable.
I think so.
The definition of organization may change,
I don't know.
Offline,
I think organizations,
when people gather offline together,
that's an organization,
I actually,
I'm curious about Jonghyun's opinion.
At MyRealTrip,
from now on,
opening a camp,
gradually releasing the intent,
you made that decision.
Having made that decision,
how it differs from the existing organization,
I was curious.
I was curious about that.
I'm curious how the structure changes.
As you might have expected, they're quite confused.
And so it seems like many are leaving.
Actually, that's how I felt.
Tearing down and rebuilding.
I think all our members agree that we need to adapt to change.
I don't think they're resisting this.
But I think they're struggling because they don't know how,
and thinking that the company should present this to them?
I kind of thought that too.
But actually right now,
well, how has the world changed?
Changes of a week, month or two are happening continuously now,
that's a bit hard to expect.
But what should I say?
One proposition I'm thinking about is,
when people work with people,
if there's a dependency, productivity drops by 10x, I think.
That's the productivity difference I felt between the Echo Delta project
and when solving my own problems by myself.
Because it's so clear, right?
I'll go develop this.
Please do this.
I'll develop it.
By when?
By next Monday.
When it comes, of course you won't like it.
Then you explain that in words again,
they receive that feedback and bring it back in a few days,
then you won't like it again.
Continuously organizing these in your head and speaking them out,
and then understanding that with completely leaked data,
and after a few days with whatever wrong information
mixed in together,
comes out as some implementation,
but actually just thinking in your head,
giving feedback when thoughts come up right away,
and then getting results back in 1 minute, right?
I think things will go more that way.
Of course, and everyone knows,
like Seojin, 1-person companies will keep emerging, not necessarily in big markets,
such companies will keep appearing,
from an entrepreneur's perspective, the pressure must be immense.
So attempts to keep downsizing organizations will continue,
and how far will it shrink is a bit of a concern, a thought,
I do have that concern.
But I worked as a 1-person team for a very long time.
Then I hired one intern,
and at that time, the perception that the team was running well,
leadership had that perception.
And the moment that person left, it felt like the team stopped,
they said they felt that.
And it actually was a bit like that.
Some programs like case sharing sessions were put on hold,
things like that.
Looking at this, in a way,
while there are issues from not delegating enough to AI,
I heard in some podcast before,
what can humans do, when asked that,
having a will and manifesting it,
I think I heard something like that.
The difference between having that point at one, two,
and three, there seems to be a difference.
Each person with their own will,
with their own thoughts, using AI or not,
giving each other feedback,
the creative things that can emerge from there,
there definitely seems to be synergy.
For me, right now it's a 3-person team.
This is the biggest team now.
3 people, 3 feels to me like this might be the limit, I thought.
Very good.
If anyone has more questions, let me ask first.
Thank you for the great comments.
I'm Baek Yunho, running a company called SquareLight.
I use Claude, GPT, Gemini CLI, and Codex,
usually Claude Code, and if it doesn't work, I call Codex.
If Codex doesn't work, I try Gemini,
and if that doesn't work, I go back to Claude Code.
If the context gets too big, I make sub-agents too,
and try using skills,
for dependent ones, I use MCP Context 7 or similar,
but while juggling all this, eventually,
I also try Ultra Think as a last resort,
then that day just comes to a halt.
But when it ultimately doesn't get fixed, I'm really curious how all the speakers handle it.
Still, when it ultimately doesn't get fixed, the project size gets too big too,
like you mentioned, even making module-sized
separate Claude Code instances,
eventually as it grows,
sometimes there's no answer within these 3 models.
Of course, now we hire people with human intelligence to dig through,
between development gaps, we look,
but really, from the perspective of wanting to build an AI-native organization,
when stuck after juggling all 3,
if there are tips that broke through, please share.
The one you use most.
For now, I definitely have to look at it myself to solve it.
I've only tried up to 8 million lines, so I wouldn't know.
Actually, the project I'm running now isn't that big in size.
So there's no context issues to the point
where analysis itself gets stuck,
but what I focus on when building skills or sub-agents,
the main focus is testing.
So you mentioned thinking result-oriented,
but that test isn't unit testing.
I'm not really curious about unit tests.
End-to-end testing is a must,
and those stages need to solidly build up step by step,
if you write hundreds of thousands of lines and then test,
mistakes from the first step snowball,
or you have to roll back to zero or 0.1 base again,
so I try to pack end-to-end tests as tightly as possible.
So when making agents or skills that create technical specs,
break it into the most granular specs you can.
That's the approach I take,
and for testing, I prefer end-to-end testing,
and if full-stack frontend and backend development is needed,
then frontend uses Playwright, backend uses curl-based
bash script verification, things like that.
This is a story about engineering.
I believe all frontier models will soon code better than me.
They definitely code better than me.
Then problems they can't solve, I'm unlikely to solve by looking at them.
Then what's the problem?
They're smarter than me, so there's no chance I can solve it by looking, I think.
If I'm unlikely to solve it by looking, the only variable I can give is context,
the only thing I can give is context,
so I approach it as how to manage this well.
Most problems within the coding framework humans have created,
Claude models usually have 200k context windows,
so problems too big to fit in there are rare, I think.
Such cases exist and are solvable problems,
if the problem fits within 100k, you need to manage context well,
when it fails once, saying "hey solve this again, try that way" in multi-turn,
bad context keeps accumulating.
And everyone knows performance degrades as context lengthens,
so what methodology I use is,
when it fails once, I just have it write a failure report.
Write a failure report, save that report as a file,
open a new session, with the prompt I gave before to solve the issue,
and "I failed with this before, here's the failure report",
these two contexts compressed, I have it try solving the problem again.
Then it tries without at least that one trial-and-error,
so probability of solving increases slightly, I think.
Using multiple models is also a great method,
but managing context well like this is also a good method, I think.
And one more thing I wanted to mention,
what's the way to manage context well in code,
ultimately it's good abstraction and deduplication.
So from the start, clearly telling AI what engineering principles
you'll use to design this code, and continuously refactoring with AI,
I think you can solve context from a structural perspective.
I agree, that's how the McDonald's principle works.
The headquarters gives the menu, containing these engineering principles,
and after setting this up well,
I rarely had the problem you mentioned when I first started,
partly because models got better, but also after swapping cheap models wisely,
it doesn't happen.
I totally agree with that.
Ultimately, all actions are activities creating higher information value,
you want to create higher value information from what you have.
From a product perspective, making frontend,
so what level of abstraction is the optimal trade-off point,
intuitively grasping that seems important,
so I don't know coding well.
I only know Python.
I need to make Streamlit, dashboards, web things,
so what I mainly do is "you're a frontend, backend, full-stack developer",
"if you had to explain a specific project to another LLM model,
structure the elements composing this project,
and write me a prompt that can organize each as a markdown file",
then I do Docs, LLM Docs,
architecture, backend, API call, rules, frontend, logic,
it all comes out like that.
I don't know, but feeding that abstracted info to GPT and asking,
it solves problems,
just copying and pasting the error message below that chat,
doing it 100 times, 20 times, like you did.
But the key is even if I don't know the right abstraction logic,
it knows, so "write it with that logic."
"You're a frontend developer, and full-stack."
It writes amazingly well.
Anyway, development needs architecture,
and backend and API call logic seem to be needed.
But ultimately,
ultimately there are points where I get stuck too.
Building that, there comes a moment it can't speak too,
since there's the concept of comments and refactoring,
ultimately I resonate with having to look yourself,
anyway it can't exceed my capability by much.
So when I'm stuck at that extreme point,
the minimum knowledge of frontend, backend, API needed at that moment,
"do I need to study this?" and it tells me everything.
I study that and just rebuild from scratch.
First time took 10 days,
so what? Rebuilding from scratch takes a day or two anyway.
That's unlearning and the concept of context abstraction, information abstraction.
We've done Q&A, for more curious things,
we'll now have networking time,
feel free to talk directly with the speakers,
or chat with people around you.
So from now on, freely network,
not sure how much time we'll give,
we've prepared about 30 minutes for networking.
And I'm originally from a developer background.
So developers have this performance thing,
there's a session called lightning talks.
The key is you take the mic and say what you want to say,
but the key is everyone does their own thing.
So if you want to attract attention, come up and do a lightning talk,
the mic is here, feel free to come up,
but there's a strict 3-minute time limit.
That's the charm of lightning talks.
So from now on, our speakers and attendees,
please network freely.