Hello. I'm Dongwoon Choi. You can call me Colin.
I'm currently working at Samyang Foods.
Samyang Foods, Buldak is famous, but it seems far from AI.
But I'll briefly share what I'm working on.
I titled it this way. What does this mean?
I posted an article on LinkedIn.
Samyang Foods, Buldak is doing great, but who would want to come work as a software developer?
IT recruitment wasn't working. We were serious about it though.
So I started posting articles, and they did well.
If you're curious, you can check out my LinkedIn.
But I said our calculators were confiscated so we could only use Excel, so I brought that as the title.
What this means is
I came to Samyang Foods with a somewhat unique background.
And then
But suddenly
they're talking about digital IT and stuff.
saying they want to build something.
So we need to deliver meaningful results by year-end.
But we only have 6 months, there's me and a designer,
and then there's that handsome long-haired gentleman sitting over there.
So we need to build something with just the three of us.
At first, naturally we thought about outsourcing development.
So we met with all kinds of companies.
But everyone was just trying to rip us off.
These guys have money and know nothing.
These guys just have money.
They both made a lot of money but now they're doing something weird.
They kept coming at us like that.
So I thought, wow, we have no choice.
The answer is to go the AI native path.
Cursor and Claude Code are working so well.
There's no other way, let's quickly accept this.
Let's accept it, and if it doesn't work, we'll just quit.
And then we have no existing legacy.
Manufacturing companies don't know anything about IT software development.
So this is originally how we do it.
I thought this would work.
So let's go, and I started with Seongju sitting over there.
So the three of us, including our designer, came to an agreement.
Since we have no time and we're busy,
everything in code.
Everyone uses Cursor and Claude Code.
No Figma, Notion, Jira, none of that crap.
Everything through chat. That's how we started.
So as we went on, what was really important was
let's throw away all the old ways.
If we don't throw it away, we can't survive.
We burned our bridges.
If we don't do this, we'll all quit anyway.
That's what we did.
So as I mentioned earlier,
we gave up PRD, Figma, development, details, everything.
Don't write meeting notes, we don't need that.
We only talk through builds.
We don't need anything but builds.
Whether it's meeting notes or Figma files, code is what's real.
All those things never get updated anyway,
they were just painful.
What's the point of all that?
We can just communicate everything through code.
So we only talk through builds,
only through code.
Fortunately, both our designer and I,
we don't know how to code at all.
But we quickly accepted that there's no other way.
Because we accepted it, we tried this approach.
And it worked.
So we actually built an MVP in one month
and launched a service targeting TikTok creators in the US market.
So the company was surprised too.
Oh, this could be done in one month?
So I said, yes, this is how it works.
You don't need to pay much to outsiders.
Just let us use a lot of tokens.
That's what I told them.
In that situation, a problem arose.
Oh, how should I explain this?
And then I realized something.
What are the core competencies? After trying it, I felt
exactly two things.
Taste and judgment. That's what I found.
AI pours out answers incredibly fast, right?
So ultimately, what humans need to do is
is this right? Or wrong? You need to tell it precisely.
Do I like this? Do I not like this? Or is it correct? Is it wrong?
You need to communicate this.
And especially when it comes to design,
there's the realm of taste.
So we need to have clear taste.
And for development architecture and such things,
there's right and wrong.
So making those judgments quickly was important.
So whether you're a prompt engineer,
or can't use models, can't use MCP, none of that matters.
First, like us, switching your mindset is the best approach.
That's what we felt.
And fortunately, the three of us had enough
experience and capability to switch our mindset.
So we proceeded with quick judgment and taste.
But then I ran into another issue.
The first month went well.
But as it became two months, three months,
gradually everyone's style started to differ.
Individual techniques started to emerge.
So as we started to diverge a bit,
we brought in freelancers to work with us.
So about five or six people
started committing to GitHub, to the repo.
And I thought, oh, I tried this and it works.
So our team's data analysts
and other non-developer roles also started committing.
So I just told them to do it.
Then gradually it started becoming chaos.
I think many of you have probably experienced this,
when multiple people use it, chaos ensues.
So I thought, oh, we need systematization.
We need something.
It was around September.
What should we do? Should we go back to the old ways?
Because of this, should I go back to using Notion and Jira
and Figma that I used before?
I was tempted.
One evening, I was eating at McDonald's,
and it suddenly hit me. Oh, this is it! This is it.
Whether you eat McDonald's in Seoul Forest, Gangnam, or New York,
it's all the same, right? The Big Mac tastes the same everywhere.
Couldn't we make it like that?
So McDonald's solved this problem the best, right?
That's what I thought.
So we decided to create a McDonald's franchise model.
Here, the headquarters, branch manager, someone like Baek Jong-won,
the person who sends down manuals from franchise headquarters,
that's the Tech Lead sitting over there.
The rest of us, non-developers and non-engineers,
we just manage our branches as branch managers.
And the part-timers there are just coding agents.
That's the idea.
So we proceeded this way.
The workflow principles can't be complex because we can't understand it, so it's very simple.
Number 1, gather everything into one context.
We have two things we call Source of Truth.
One is we record all meetings
and after recording, we dump everything into Google Notebook LM.
We didn't have time to build legacy systems.
So Google Notebook LM, let's just use what's available quickly.
We dump everything into the repo and Notebook LM.
All the meeting notes are in there.
So why we're trying to do this work,
if you throw a prompt into Notebook LM, it tells you.
We start work from there.
And for deliverables, we really don't use Notion, Figma, Jira.
Nothing. Only GitHub.
So we gather everything in GitHub.
So this is how we created our McDonald's.
You can see our signature menu items like Start Feature and such.
We've broken everything down.
And when it comes to how McDonald's maintains uniformity,
if one part-timer had to make a Big Mac, everyone would do it differently.
But someone only takes orders, someone only toasts buns, someone only cooks patties.
That's how they maintain uniformity.
We actually saved a lot on token costs.
We used a lot of tokens and thought it wasn't good.
Too expensive. And slow. The higher the model.
If you break it down like this, cheap and fast models can run quickly, quickly, quickly.
Speed was really, really important for us.
So we broke it down like this and used cheap and fast models.
Things like Cursor's Composer are so fast.
Really great. We just run it quickly and use it.
That's how we did it.
As we went on, it's fast to say too, right?
I'll take my time and speak quickly.
So we did mergers and acquisitions.
We had multiple repositories.
McDonald's wasn't there, it was in the app we made before.
And there were several other agents or different types of repos.
But we realized this.
Oh, we need to merge and acquire a lot into McDonald's.
Let's go with a monorepo.
We merged all the multiple repositories into one.
Analysis that analysts used, Agent that analysts used,
our app, we bundled everything together.
After bundling, now all the context is in here, everyone's stuff is in here.
Based on this, we pull out what we need and use it.
As we did this, whoever comes can do it right away.
Since full-time hiring is nearly impossible for us,
we have no choice but to use freelancers.
We're working with Goobong's team.
Kwontae sitting over there, Jake, as soon as he came, he immediately did Start Feature.
On the first day, he just built a feature right away.
As a freelancer.
Oh right, this is it. This is McDonald's.
When you work part-time at McDonald's, you start working right away on the first day.
We really, really needed to make it like that.
In a reality where full-time hiring is impossible, this is all we can do.
So we went this way.
So in conclusion, there are several things I can say,
but the biggest thing is first, going to an environment where I have no choice but to throw away my old ways.
That's what it is.
If I had 10 engineers on the team, I can clearly tell I would never have done this.
We're doing this because we don't have them on the team.
Second, just close your mind and just build something first.
Anyway, in a world where there are no right answers regarding AI, trying it is the most important.
Third, the era of dividing engineers and non-engineers is over.
This is too old-fashioned. Everyone writes code. All 12 out of 12 on our team can write code.
Because it's not code,
you can talk in Korean too.
So you can use Korean.
So give everyone a Cursor project and if you're frustrated, you build it.
There was something from the earlier presentation, right?
If you're frustrated, you build it. That's really good.
And we put everything into our monorepo, merged it with McDonald's,
so pick out the prompts and elements in there and build what you want.
That's the essence of it.
That's it.
The end.